Task number 33.
So, I'm going to read the function “while”
and try to understand how it works.
First, we have the type signature.
We have something of type “a”.
So, this “a” doesn't specify anything. This
“a” could be a String. It could be an Integer.
It could be a tuple that contains
two things of two different types.
And then we have a function
that takes something of type “a”
the same “a” as here and returns True or False.
So, you could imagine this function is
some kind of a “checker”. It checks
whether something is fulfilled or not.
And then we have a function that takes something
of type “a” and returns something of type “IO a”.
For me,
if this were my first time reading this task,
I'd say this means that the function here is
going to be the body of the loop because we
know what a while-loop is from other courses…
from programming in general. And this “IO” here
should indicate that this function has a do-block.
And at the end of the do-block, we're going
to have “return” something of type “a”.
And then finally, we're going to have “IO
a”. So, “while” takes these three parameters.
The “a” is going to be just
something of type “a” (anything).
And “p” is going to be the
predicate... the “checker”…
this function that takes something of type “a”
and returns True or False. And “body”
is going to be the body of the loop.
So, here we have the main operations, the
things that we want to do with this loop.
And here we have “loop a” because
“a” is going to be the only variable
that's going to change in value
every time we go through the loop.
So, “body” is going to stay the
same always because it's just
the function that we're going to
apply, and “p” is the predicate,
but “a” is going to be the initial value
on which the function depends, and
the while-loop knows when to stop.
Now “loop x” is a function that takes
just one argument “x” and then it checks
whether “x” fulfills the predicate “p”.
And if it does, then we go to this do-block. In
this new block, we do two things: first we apply
the function “body”, which should be given as an
argument by whoever uses this function “while”,
and we just apply it to “x”,
and we store the result in a new “x”, and
then we do “loop” again on this new “x”.
But if the “x” doesn't fulfill the predicate, then
we just return “x” itself. So, what we're saying is:
take this “x” and see if it
fulfills “p”, and then if it does,
then change something in it
using the function “body”,
and then store the new value here, and apply
“loop” again to this new value. Otherwise,
if it doesn't fulfill the condition, then just
return it as it is. Now we have “undefined”
four times, and we need to replace them with
something useful to make the function work.
And “while” takes, as you can see… it
takes three arguments… three parameters.
So, this means these three “undefined”s are
going to be the parameters for “while”,
and the last one here is going to
specify the type of this do-block,
which in turn specifies the type of “main”
itself. What could this “undefined” be?
Well… if you look at the lecture
slides, you can see that we have
some functions like “put string” (putStr)
which has the type “IO” and also “print”,
but for example not “read line”
(readLn) because “readLn” is
going to give us something of type “IO a”.
So, the first thing I'm going
to give to this function “while”
is going to be this “a”
which is the initial value.
And this “a” is going to be
affected by the function “body”,
and then the value of this “a”
is going to change every time.
And depending on this value,
the loop is going to stop.
I'm going to use this “a”… this
parameter here as a counter to count how
many numbers we have entered already.
So, this means we start with 0, and
we're going to enter “n” numbers.
Let's see how we're going to express
that. And this parameter is going to
be the predicate that checks
whether we reached “n” or not.
Okay now, let's write the function.
So, I'm going to do “i” for “index”.
And then we check whether “i”
is still smaller than “n”.
So, this is the “n” we're talking about.
And “i” is going to be whatever
this predicate gets as a parameter.
Now, the parameter “body” is going to be a
function. Let's look at the type signature.
So, it's going to be a function
that takes something of type “a”
and gives us something of type “IO a”.
So, it basically changes the value
of “a” and does some other stuff.
But here we have a problem:
this “i” is not a String.
So, we cannot do concatenation with another
String. So, we need to do “show i”.
And now we read a number from the user.
We say “x read line” (x <- readLn).
Here we have a “return”. But we have a
problem here which is that we want to send
two values to be used later
in the next run of the loop,
which are “x” and “i”. “i” is the counter and “x”
is the value of the factor that the user entered.
The solution to this problem is to use
something that counts as one parameter,
but it actually contains information of two
things. And for this, we can use a tuple.
So, I'm going to put the index first and
I'm going to put the value of “x” second.
And this means we also have to change the
initial value, which is this “a” we talked about.
So, it's going to be a tuple. It's
still going to have zero as an index.
And it's going to have one because
this here is going to be multiplied by the
other factors that the user is going to enter,
and in multiplication, this “1” here is
a neutral element, which means it doesn't
affect the result of multiplication.
So, if we were doing addition
instead of multiplication, we would
have “0” here because zero is
the neutral element in addition.
And now we also have to change this one here. So,
this one doesn't take just an Integer… an index.
Now it takes a tuple that has the index
first and then it has whatever as a second.
We don't care and we still check whether this
“i” (this index) is still smaller than n.
Now if you look here, what we just did is send
the index as it is to the next run of the loop,
and we send the x as it is to the next
run of the loop, which is totally useless.
This means the loop is going to be
stuck because “i” is not changing,
and x that the user entered is
just going to be sent as it is.
There's no multiplication happening. This
means this here needs to be changed.
So, this is going to be “i+1” which means:
the next run, this index is going to be 1,
and the next one is going to be
2, and so on until we reach n.
And here, this function “body” is still
taking just one parameter which is
“i” (the index). This is not good.
So, we need to do i and the old value of x which
is the factor that the user entered the last time…
the last one of this loop.
Let's call it y. So, this means here we
want the new x which the user has just
entered to be it with the old x which is y.
Now all we have to do is change this
last “undefined”. So, I’m going to write
“putStrLn” here.
And then, yes, it's going to be a String.
So, we say: your result multiplication of,
and then “show n” which is this n here (the
number of factors that the user wanted).
And then we do concatenation again.
And then we do “show” again.
And now we want the result.
How do we get the result? Well… the result
is stored in this here… this “returned”.
So, if you look here, this whole thing
is just applying “while” to these three parameters
and then storing the result in this variable.
But if you look at this line here, we have returned
a tuple, which contains the index and the result.
So, this is going to be the final
result because every time it's
multiplying the new factor with the
old factor that the user entered.
This means here it's also going to be a tuple.
And to deal with tuples, you can use
'fst' ("first") and 'snd' ("second").
So, the first of this tuple, for example,
gives you this. And the second gives you this.
So, “return” has the index as first and
the result as second. This means we write
the second of returned.
Now let's do a final check. So,
the type signature of while is “a”.
And then something that takes “a” and returns
Boolean (Bool). Something that takes “a”.
It returns “IO” of “a”. And finally, we get “IO a”.
Let's see. So, here we have something “a”.
And just like I said, “a” doesn't specify
anything. So, “a” could be a tuple.
There's no problem with that.
And then we have the predicate. This is a function
that takes something of the same type here.
It's a tuple and it returns True or
False. And finally, we have “body”
which should take something of type “a”
and return something of type “IO a”.
This is type “a”, and this here is “IO a”
because this is “a”. And we have “return” here.
So, everything looks fine.
Okay now let's test it.
So, let's do “main”. Let's say
I want to multiply four numbers.
2, 2, 3, 5.
As you can see, it is working. I still need to
move this a little bit away from the word factor.
Okay let's do it. Okay, space here and space here.
And let's reload “main”. Let's say five numbers.
2, 2, 3, 3, 5.
Okay I still have a problem here which is:
whenever we enter the first factor,
it says 0, the second, it says 1.
So, it's always one less than it's
supposed to be. Let's fix it too.
Okay “main”. 4… 2, 2, 3, 5. Yes, it's working!